A Guide to Ford Foundation records, Rights and Social Justice Program, AIDS Initiative FA1418
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Rights and Social Justice Program, AIDS Initiative
1986-1991
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1418
3.42 Cubic Feet 9 document containers
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into one series: National-Community AIDS Partnership Files
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains reports, correspondence, press clippings, and staff subject files related to the National-Community AIDS Partnership and the National AIDS Network.
The collection also includes materials regarding philanthropic responses to the AIDS crisis more broadly.
Biographical / Historical
In June 1987, the Ford Foundation appointed a panel of experts to examine needs posed by the AIDS epidemic. The panel determined that private philanthropy could step in to provide social services, practical support to individuals with AIDS and their families, and design community education programs.
The Ford Foundation Board of Trustees established a National-Community AIDS Partnership (NCAP) to support community-based efforts to provide preventive education and social services for people with AIDS.
The Ford Foundation initially contributed $2 million to the Partnership, but ultimately contributed $15 million to strengthen philanthropic support for AIDS-related needs between 1988 and 1998. The Partnership, composed of private foundations and corporate donors, was housed at the National AIDS Network (NAN) in Washington, DC.
In 1988, the National-Community AIDS Partnership targeted locations included: Atlanta, Connecticut, Greater Cleveland, Minnesota, Northern California, New York/New Jersey, Southern California and Southwest Border States, and Washington, DC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2018 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2018:018.
HIV/AIDS; HIV/AIDS -- Research; Ford Foundation
- National-Community AIDS Partnership Files, 1986-1991; 1
  - Compendium of Developments for the National-Community AIDS Partnership Sites, 1988 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Atlanta, Connecticut, Greater Cleveland, Minnesota, Northern California, New York/New Jersey, Southern California and Southwest Border States, Washington, D.C.
  - Meeting of the National-Community AIDS Partnership National Advisory Committee - Summary Report, 1988 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Press Clippings - Ford Foundation AIDS Grant Programs, 1988 April-May (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Michael Seltzer - Correspondence, 1988 January-March (Box 1, Folder 4)
    United Hospital Fund and Shepard Smith
  - Michael Seltzer - Press Clippings, 1987 August (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Michael Seltzer - Second Meeting of Ford Foundation Consultants on AIDS Policy, 1987 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Michael Seltzer - Meeting the AIDS Challenge: Opportunities for Action and Intervention: A Report to the Ford Foundation from its Consultants Group on AIDS Policy (Proofed with Corrections), 1987 September (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Michael Seltzer - Consultants Report - Working Draft, 1987 December (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Michael Seltzer - Press Clippings, 1986 November-1987 August (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Michael Seltzer - AIDS in the Bay Area: An Overview and Needs Analysis, 1987 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Submitted to Northern California Grantmakers, Prepared by Nancy J. Frank
  - Michael Seltzer - The Status of AIDS in New York City, 1987 February (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Internal memo prepared for Distribution Committee of New York Community Trust
  - Michael Seltzer - Internal Memo Prepared for Jim Furman at MacArthur, 1987 May-July (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Correspondence with Ted Hearne
  - Michael Seltzer - Preliminary Draft - Meeting the Challenge: Foundation Responses to Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome, 1987 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Michael Seltzer - Meeting the Challenge: Foundation Responses to Acquired Deficiency Syndrome, 1987 October (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Michael Seltzer - Medical Answers About AIDS pamphlet, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Michael Seltzer - American Society of Law and Medicine, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Law, Medicine, and Health Care: AIDS Law and Policy, Volume 15, Number I-2; American Society of Law and Medicine Annual 1986-1987; AIDS and Public Policy Journal Vol 2 Fall-Winter 1987 No. 4; Public Health and the Law - AIDS Screening, Confidentiality, and the Duty to Warn; Public Health and the Law - Legal Control Measure for AIDS: Reporting Requirements, Surveillance, Quarantine, and Regulation of Public Meeting Places, Vaccination for AIDS: Legal and Ethical Challenges from the Test Tube, to the Human Subject, Through to the Marketplace; Compulsory Premarital Screening for the Human Immunodeficiency Virus; Law, Medicine, and Health Care Vol 14, No. 5-6 - AIDS Science and Epidemiology
  - Michael Seltzer - White House Response to Watkins Commission's Report and Manhattan, Inc. Article, 1988 August (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence - Michael Seltzer, 1987 July-December (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The Invisible Emergency: Children and AIDS in New York, Citizens' Committee for Children of New York, Inc., 1987 April (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - AIDS and the Third World, Panos Dossier 1, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, 1987 March-July (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Planning for New York Regional Association of Grantmaker's (NYRAG) Future, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The Second Stage of the Epidemic, Homosexuals and AIDS, Katie Leishman, The Atlantic Monthly, 1987 February (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - The Personal and Social Costs of the AIDS Epidemic: A Different Kind of Currency, June E. Osborn, The Internist, 1987 April (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - The AIDS Pandemic: An Internationalist Approach to Disease Control, Lincoln C. Chen, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Face of AIDS: One Year in the Epidemic, Newsweek, 1987 August 10 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Throwing Money at AIDS, Lee Smith, Fortune, 1987 August 31 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - AIDS in Africa: Anatomy of the Virus, Charting the Epidemic, Newscientist, 1987 March 26 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Meeting the AIDS Challenge: Opportunities for Action and Intervention, a Report to the Ford Foundation from its Consultants Group on AIDS Policy, 1987 September (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Lists of AIDS Grants, Research, and Educational Programs, 1987 May-December (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - National-Community AIDS Partnership National Committee Meeting and Fund Committee, 1988 June 21 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - AIDS National Funders, 1987 November-1989 March (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Meeting minutes, project objectives, correspondence, and press releases
  - The National Community AIDS Partnership: A Fund for Care and Preventative Education, A Request for Support, Submitted by the National AIDS Network, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - AIDS Initiative Mailing List, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1987 August-1988 June (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Andrea Taylor, Beverly Levine
  - National Community AIDS Partnership Materials, 1987 November-1988 May (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Agenda for AIDS Program of the US Conference of Mayors, Naught for Your Comfort: Social Scenarios on the Future of AIDS, National-Community AIDS Partnership Clippings, The Elements of a Comprehensive Community AIDS Prevention Campaign Prepared by Larry L. Bye
  - Compendium of Developments for the National-Community AIDS Partnership Sites, 1988 June 21 (Box 3, Folder 37-38)
    Atlanta, Connecticut, Greater Cleveland, Minnesota, Northern California, New York/New Jersey, Southern California and Southwest Border States, Washington, DC
  - National Community AIDS Partnership Correspondence and Fundraising Summary, 1988 May-June (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - National-Community AIDS Partnership - Precis, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - National-Community AIDS Partnership - Purpose, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Shepard Forman Letter, 1987 December-1988 March (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Letters regarding joining the National AIDS Fund/National Committee overseeing the National AIDS Fund, Shepard Forman's listings, correspondence with foundations, corporate leaders, and professors of public health, mailings under Shepard Forman's signature
  - Susan V. Berresford Letter, 1987 December-1988 January (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Susan Berresford's Address Listings, mailings under Susan Berresford's signature, requests for response to "The AIDS Challenge: A Foundation Response"
  - Ford Foundation AIDS Initiative Press Releases, 1988 April-May (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - National AIDS Committee - Lists, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - AIDS - Letter (6529), 1988 January-May (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Ford Foundation's Response to AIDS statement, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Internal Correspondence, 1987 February-1988 October (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Stuart Burden, Christopher Mobley, Jon Friedman, Terry Lisniewski, Margaret B. Lowe, Shepard Forman, Richard Horovitz, William S. Saint, William Saint, William Duggan, Susan Berresford
  - National Community AIDS Partnership, 1988 May-1989 July (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Steering committee meeting agenda July 1989, The National-Community AIDS Partnership: A Progress Report for Corporate Leaders - June 1989, The Year in Review - June 1989, National Community AIDS Partnership Mailing List, National Funder Questionnaire, Letters to potential donors
  - The National-Community AIDS Partnership: A Fund for Care and Preventive Education pamphlet, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - National AIDS Network, Inc. Correspondence and Meeting Agendas, 1990 February-August (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Meeting of the National-Community AIDS Partnership National Advisory Committee - Summary Report, 1988 June 21 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - National Community AIDS Partnership Meeting, December 13-14, 1988, 1988 August-1989 March (Box 4, Folder 53-57)
    List of grant awards for Northern California, Connecticut, Washington, D.C., and New York City; Press clippings; Memo from Paula Van Ness with attachment; Sub-committee Reports - Expansion, Evaluation, and Corporate Outreach; Needs Assessments - Cleveland: The Cleveland Foundation and Minnesota: The Minneapolis Foundation and The Saint Paul Foundation; News Release from the National Research Council; Meeting agendas; National Organizations Responding to AIDS (NORA) press packet prepared for President George H. W. Bush; Robert Wood Johnson Foundation list of grant awards for AIDS Prevention and Service Projects; Schedules for December 13-14, 1988 meeting; Memos from Midge Taylor; Mailing #4 National Community AIDS Partnership - Memos from Paula Van Ness, Announcements, and Resource Lists
  - National Community AIDS Partnership - First Year, 1989 March-June (Box 4, Folder 58-59)
    Meeting agendas, Strategic Options for the National Community AIDS Partnership: The Next Decade, A Background Paper for Discussion by National Funders; Agenda for Strategic Thinking Meeting; Funders Concerned About AIDS bulletin; Recommendations to Establish an Evaluation Mechanism for the National-Community AIDS Partnership; First Year Report Materials
  - Dr. David E. Rogers, Cornell University Medical College - Correspondence, 1988 April-1990 March (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - National Committee - Shepard Forman File, 1988 March-November (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Presidential Commission on AIDS - Draft, 1988 June 27 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Chairman's Draft Recommendations for the Final Report of the Presidential Commission on the HIV Epidemic (2 copies), 1988 June 2 (Box 5, Folder 63-64)
  - Miscellaneous Shepard Forman Memos and Correspondence, 1988 February-April (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Requests for AIDS Materials, 1988 May (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Duplicates of Community Reports, 1988 May-June (Box 5, Folder 67-68)
  - Miscellaneous, 1988 July-October (Box 5, Folder 69)
    Minnesota Council of Churches; Private Sector Leadership Conference on AIDS - September 16, 1988 Agenda; Hispanic AIDS Committee for Education and Resources (HACER) Newsletter Volume 1; The Role of HIV Testing in AIDS Prevention, Institute of Criminal Science, University of Copenhagen; National AIDS Network Skills Building Conference October 1988; New York Community Trust
  - Centers for Disease Control Request for Proposal, 1988 March-August (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Miscellaneous Shepard Forman Memos and Correspondence, 1988 April-June (Box 6, Folder 71)
    Statement of Erol Ricketts, Assistant Director, Equal Opportunity Division, The Rockefeller Foundation before the Presidential Commission on the Human Immunodeficiency Virus Epidemic on Societal and Legal Issues of AIDS: Costs to Society; Presentation to Trustees in June 1988; Correspondence with other foundations
  - Design Industries Foundation for AIDS (DIFFA) Correspondence, 1988 August (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Nick Rango - AIDS in New York State Through 1987, 1988 October 6 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Suki Ports - AIDS and Women, 1988 October 6 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - KCTS - Seattle - Jeff Gentes, 1988 August 19 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Ed Brandt - University of Maryland, 1988 August 18 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Edward Burger - Georgetown, 1988 October 5 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - St. Paul Foundation, 1988 August-September (Box 6, Folder 78)
    St. Paul press clippings and A Pastoral Letter: The Church and the Homosexual Person
  - William Bondurant - Mary Reynolds Babcock Foundation, 1988 March-August (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Kansas City - AIDS Initiative and Honeywell Contact, 1988 January-July (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - National AIDS Network - Recommendation for Grant Action Forms, 1988 February (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - National AIDS Network - October 18, 1988 Meeting, 1988 October 18 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - National AIDS Network - Technical Assistance Initiative, 1988 September 14 (Box 6, Folder 83-85)
  - National AIDS Network Skills Building Conference pamphlet, 1988 October 20-23 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - National AIDS Network Technical Assistance Series - Part I Client Services - Buddy Programs: Volunteer Peer Support Programs for HIV-Related Illness, Michael J. Sieradzki, 1988 July (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - National AIDS Network Directory, AIDS Education and Service Organizations, AIDS Lifeline, 1988 January (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - National AIDS Network Directory, AIDS Education and Service Organizations, AIDS Lifeline - Fall, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - The National-Community AIDS Partnership: A Fund for Care and Preventive Education - A Request for Support, undated (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - National AIDS Network - Executive Summary, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Americans Who Care: Volunteers Working in the Battle Against AIDS, A Project of the National AIDS Network (3 copies), 1987 (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - National AIDS Network Pamphlets, Newsletters, and Promotional Materials, 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 93-94)
    Folder 93: An Introduction to the Network; List of Winter 1987 Publications; National AIDS Network/Stamp Out AIDS Grant Guidelines; National AIDS Network Survey; Pre-Grant Inventory Correspondence; The National AIDS Network Monitor (A Quarterly Publication of the AIDS Network), Fall 1987-Winter 1989
    Folder 94: National AIDS Network Multi-Cultural NOTES on AIDS Service and Education, June 1987-August 1988; Network News (A Semi-Monthly Publication of the National AIDS Network), June 1987-March 1989; Heads, Hearts, and Hand: Profiles of Community-Based Racial and Ethnic Minority Responses to AIDS; Ad Council - Public Service News: Unprecedented National Ad Campaign Promotes the Use of Condoms to Help Stop AIDS
  - National AIDS Network - Work Plan Fiscal Year 1988, November 1987 Board Meeting, 1987 November (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - National-Community AIDS Partnership - Richard Horovitz, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 96-97)
    Folder 96: Notes; National-Community AIDS Partnership: A Fund for Care and Preventive Education; Compendium of developments for National-Community AIDS Partnership sites
    Folder 97: United Conference of Mayors - AIDS Program Agenda; The Elements of a Comprehensive Community AIDS Prevention Campaign Prepared by Larry L. Bye; National-Community AIDS Partnership Clips - April 1988
  - Paula Van Ness - Correspondence, Reports, and Clippings, 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 98-100)
    Folder 98: National-Community AIDS Partners; NCAP Advisory Committee Memo; Summary Report from June 21st meeting of the National Advisory Committee; Order form for Blaming Others: Prejudice, race, and worldwide AIDS; Article "Mounting Safer Sex Campaigns in Areas with Religious, Political and/or Legal Constraints," by Mick Quinlan, Gay Health Action, Dublin, Ireland and John David Dupree, AIDSCOM, Washington, D.C.; Southern California Request for Proposal; Copy of President Reagan's 10-point action plan for implementing the recommendations of the Presidential Commission on the HIV epidemic; Article, "Foundations set $1.5 million goal for AIDS groups," St. paul Pioneer Press Dispatch; Registration Packet and poster for the National AIDS Network's Skills Building Conference for Community Based AIDS Service Organizations to be held Oct. 20-23, 1988 in New Orleans
    Folder 99: Memos and Correspondence with foundations
    Folder 100: National AIDS Network Grant Action Forms
  - National-Community AIDS Partnership - Memos, 1991 January-March (Box 8, Folder 101)
    Upcoming Meetings; 1990 National Advisory Committee Meeting Minutes
  - The National Community AIDS Partnership: Communication Audit and Plan, 1990 December (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - National-Community Partnership National Advisory Committee, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 103, Box 9, Folder 104)
    Folder 103: Resolutions for Consideration - December 7, 1990; Proposed Inter-AIDS Agency Retreat; Board of Trustees/National Advisory Committee - Nominations - November 30, 1990; AIDS Task Force - Program Report 1989-1990, Northern California Grantmakers; National Community AIDS Partnership Mailing List; Meeting Materials for December 7, 1990
    Folder 104: Memos and Correspondence - Follow-up to the National Advisory Committee Meeting of December 4, 1989; Long Range Planning Subcommittee Meeting - December 6, 1990, Board of Trustees Meeting - December 7, 1990, and National Advisory Committee Meeting - December 7, 1990
  - National Community AIDS Partnership - Letters to Paula Van Ness from Partner Foundations, 1990 June-July (Box 9, Folder 105)
    United Way of Middle Tennessee, Community Foundation of New Jersey, Greater Richmond Community Foundation, Foundation for the Carolinas, Council of Michigan Foundations, The Foundation of Greater Greensboro, Inc., Technical Assistance Conference on AIDS and Mental Health Sponsored by the Ittleson Foundation 1990, Match Grant Report - Atlanta Site, The Community AIDS Partnership Project - Cleveland Site of the National Community AIDS Partnership, Connecticut AIDS Consortium, The Saint Paul Foundation, Report of the Community Foundation of New Jersey to the National Community AIDS Partnership for the Fiscal Year May 1, 1989-April 30, 1990, Northern California Grantmakers - AIDS Task Force; Eugene and Agnes E. Meyer Foundation
  - Lists of Grants Awarded to Partners in the National Community AIDS Partnership - Grant Cycle II, 1988-1990 (Box 9, Folder 106)
    Grants Awarded by the Metropolitan Atlanta Community Foundation - The Atlanta Partner of the National Community AIDS Partnership; Grants Awarded by the Cleveland Foundation - The Cleveland Partner of the National Community AIDS Partnership; Grants Awarded by the Minnesota AIDS Funding Consortium - The Minnesota Partner of the National Community AIDS Partnership; Grants Awarded by the Community Foundation of New Jersey - The New York/New Jersey Partner of the National Community AIDS Partnership; Grants Awarded by the Northern California Grantmakers - The Northern California Partner of the National Community AIDS Partnership; National Community AIDS Partnership Mailing List
  - National Community AIDS Partnership - Press Materials, 1990 April-September (Box 9, Folder 107)
    Western Reserve AIDS Foundations; May Department Stores Company Foundation Grants $200,000 to National AIDS Organizations; Private Profit Public Gain: Corporate Philanthropy in America, The Atlantic
  - National Community AIDS Partnership - Memos, 1990 August (Box 9, Folder 108)
    Materials for Meeting in Cleveland on August 27, 1990; Cleveland Foundation agreement; National Advisory Committee Meeting Minutes July 20, 1990
  - National Community AIDS Partnership - National Advisory Committee Meeting - Minutes, 1990 July 20 (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - National Community AIDS Partnership - Financial Statements, 1989 May 1-1990 April 30 (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - National Community AIDS Partnership - National Advisory Committee Meetings, 1990 January-1990 July (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - CARE Act, 1989 December-1990 March (Box 9, Folder 112)
    National Commission on Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome - Statement on the "CARE" Act of 1990; Presidential Commission on the HIV Epidemic; AIDS Action Council - Comprehensive AIDS Resources Emergency Act of 1990 (CARE) S.2240; Working Conference on Public Policy, AIDS, and Philanthropy
  - Project Director Position, 1987 September-1988 May (Box 9, Folder 113)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Personal information